One thing the world needs,
حول الشئ الذي يحتاجه العالم،
one thing this country desperately needs
أحد الأشياء التي تحتاجها هذه البلاد بشدة
is a better way
هو طريقة أفضل
of conducting our political debates.
لإجراء مناظراتنا السياسية.
We need to rediscover
نحن بحوجة لإعادة إكتشاف
the lost art of democratic argument.
الفن المفقود للجدل الديموقراطي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If you think about the arguments we have,
إذا فكرت في الجدل الذي لدينا،
most of the time it's shouting matches
في معظم الأوقات هو مباريات صراخ
on cable television,
على شبكات التلفاز،
ideological food fights on the floor of Congress.
معارك ايديولوجية على الغذاء على أرضية الكونجرس.
I have a suggestion.
أنا لدي إقتراح.
Look at all the arguments we have these days
أنظروا لكل الجدل الذي لدينا هذه الأيام
over health care,
حول الرعاية الصحية،
over bonuses and bailouts on Wall Street,
حول الحوافز وخطة الإنقاذ في وول إستريت،
over the gap between rich and poor,
حول الفارق ما بين الأثرياء والفقراء،
over affirmative action and same-sex marriage.
حول العمل الإيجابي وزواج نفس الجنس.
Lying just beneath the surface
ترقد فقط تحت سطح
of those arguments,
هذا الجدل،
with passions raging on all sides,
مع المشاعر مستعرة على كل الجبهات،
are big questions
أسئلة ضخمة
of moral philosophy,
للفلسفة الأخلاقية،
big questions of justice.
أسئلة كبيرة للعدالة.
But we too rarely
لكننا نادراً جداً
articulate and defend
نعبّر و ندافع
and argue about
ونجادل حول
those big moral questions in our politics.
هذه الأسئلة الأخلاقية الكبيرة في سياستنا.
So what I would like to do today
لذا فما أريد فعله اليوم
is have something of a discussion.
هو أن نحصل على شئ للنقاش.
First, let me take
أولاً، دعوني آخذ
a famous philosopher
فيلسوف شهير
who wrote about those questions
الذي كتب عن تلك الأسئلة
of justice and morality,
للعدالة والأخلاق،
give you a very short lecture
أعطيكم محاضرة قصيرة جداً
on Aristotle of ancient Athens,
عن أرسطو في أثينا القديمة ،
Aristotle's theory of justice,
نظرية أرسكو عن العدالة،
and then have a discussion here
ثم ندخل في نقاش هنا
to see whether Aristotle's ideas
لنرى سواء كانت أفكار أرسطو
actually inform
حقاً تبرز
the way we think and argue
الطريقة التي نفكر ونجادل
about questions today.
بها حول الأسئلة اليوم.
So, are you ready for the lecture?
إذاً، هل أنتم جاهزون للمحاضرة؟
According to Aristotle,
وفقاً لأرسطو
justice means giving people what they deserve.
العدالة تعني إعطاء الناس ما يستحقونه.
That's it; that's the lecture.
هذا كل شئ. تلك هي المحاضرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, you may say, well, that's obvious enough.
الآن، ربما تقولون، حسناً، ذلك من الطبيعي بما يكفي.
The real questions begin
تبدأ الأسئلة الحقيقية
when it comes to arguing about
عندما نأتي للجدل حول
who deserves what and why.
من يستحق ماذا ولماذا.
Take the example of flutes.
لنأخذ المثال لآلة المزمار.
Suppose we're distributing flutes.
نفترض أنكم توزعون مزامير.
Who should get the best ones?
من الذي سيأخذ أفضل مزمار؟
Let's see what people --
لنرى ما يقوله الناس--
What would you say?
ماذا ستقول؟
Who should get the best flute?
من الذي سيأخذ أفضل مزمار؟
You can just call it out.
يمكنك فقط قولها.
(Audience: Random.)
(أحد الحضور: عشوائي.)
Michael Sandel: At random. You would do it by lottery.
مايكل ساندل: بعشوائية. ستفعلونها بالقرعة.
Or by the first person to rush into the hall to get them.
أو لأول شخص يدخل إلى القاعة لأخذه.
Who else?
من أيضاً؟
(Audience: The best flute players.)
(أحد الحضور: أفضل لاعب مزمار.)
MS: The best flute players. (Audience: The worst flute players.)
مايكل: أفضل لاعب مزمار. ( الحضور: أسوأ لاعب مزمار.)
MS: The worst flute players.
مايكل: أسوأ لاعب مزمار.
How many say the best flute players?
كم منكم يقول أفضل لاعب مزمار؟
Why?
لماذا؟
Actually, that was Aristotle's answer too.
في الواقع تلك إجابة أرسطو ايضاً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But here's a harder question.
لكن ها هو سؤال أصعب.
Why do you think,
لماذا تعتقدون،
those of you who voted this way,
أؤلئك منكم الذين صوتوا بهذه الطريقة،
that the best flutes should go to the best flute players?
أن أفضل المزامير ينبغي أن تذهب لأفضل لاعبي المزامير؟
Peter: The greatest benefit to all.
بيتر: أفضل الفوائد للجميع.
MS: The greatest benefit to all.
مايكل: أفضل الفوائد للجميع.
We'll hear better music
سنستمع لموسيقى أفضل
if the best flutes should go to the best flute players.
إذا كان أفضل لاعب سيأخذ أفضل المزامير.
That's Peter? (Audience: Peter.)
ذلك بيتر؟ (الحضور: بيتر.)
MS: All right.
مايكل: حسناً.
Well, it's a good reason.
حسناً، إنه سبب وجيه.
We'll all be better off if good music is played
سنكون كلنا أفضل إذا لُعبت موسيقى جيدة
rather than terrible music.
بدلاً عن موسيقى فظيعة.
But Peter,
لكن يا بيتر،
Aristotle doesn't agree with you that that's the reason.
أرسطو لا يتفق معك بأن ذاك هو السبب.
That's all right.
ذلك صحيح.
Aristotle had a different reason
لدى أرسطو سبب مختلف
for saying the best flutes should go to the best flute players.
للقول أن أفضل المزامير ينبغي أن تذهب لأفضل لاعبي المزمار.
He said,
لقد قال،
that's what flutes are for --
لأن ذلك هو سبب وجود المزامير--
to be played well.
لكي تُلعب جيداً.
He says that to reason about
إنه يقول ذلك ليبرر عن
just distribution of a thing,
مجرد توزيع الشئ،
we have to reason about,
الذي ينبغي أن نمنطق حوله،
and sometimes argue about,
وبعض الأحيان نجادل حوله،
the purpose of the thing,
هدف الشئ،
or the social activity --
أو النشاط الإجتماعي،
in this case, musical performance.
في هذه الحالة، العرض الموسيقي.
And the point, the essential nature,
وفي الفكرة، الطبيعة الأساسية،
of musical performance
للعرض الموسيقي
is to produce excellent music.
هو أن تقدم موسيقى ممتازة.
It'll be a happy byproduct
سوف تكون نتيجة ثانوية سعيدة
that we'll all benefit.
التي ستفيدنا جميعاً.
But when we think about justice,
لكن حينما نفكر بالعدالة،
Aristotle says,
يقول أرسطو،
what we really need to think about
الذي نحتاج لنفكر به حقاً
is the essential nature of the activity in question
هو الطبيعة الأساسية للنشاط مثار الحديث
and the qualities that are worth
والصفات التي تستحق
honoring and admiring and recognizing.
التكريم والتقدير والعرفان.
One of the reasons
أحد الأسباب
that the best flute players should get the best flutes
التي ينبغي لأفضل لاعب مزمار الحصول على أفضل المزامير
is that musical performance
هو أن العرض الموسيقي
is not only to make the rest of us happy,
ليس فقط لجعلنا سعداء،
but to honor
لكن لتكريم
and recognize
وتقدير
the excellence
التميز
of the best musicians.
لأفضل الموسيقيين.
Now, flutes may seem ... the distribution of flutes
الآن، ربما تبدو المزامير...توزيع المزامير
may seem a trivial case.
ربما تبدو قضية ساذجة.
Let's take a contemporary example
لنأخذ مثالاً معاصراً
of the dispute about justice.
للنزاع حول العدالة.
It had to do with golf.
لديه صلة بلعبة الغولف.
Casey Martin -- a few years ago,
كاسي مارتن-- قبل عدة سنوات،
Casey Martin --
كاسي مارتن--
did any of you hear about him?
هل سمع به أي منكم؟
He was a very good golfer,
لقد كان لاعب غولف جيد حداً،
but he had a disability.
لكن كانت لديه إعاقة.
He had a bad leg, a circulatory problem,
لديه ساق سيئة، مشكلة في الدورة الدموية،
that made it very painful
الذي جعل من المؤلم جداً
for him to walk the course.
بالنسبة له المشي في المعلب.
In fact, it carried risk of injury.
في الواقع، لقد حوت مخاطر الإصابة.
He asked the PGA,
لقد طلب من رابطة الغولف للمحترفين،(PGA)
the Professional Golfers' Association,
رابطة الغولف للمحترفين،
for permission to use a golf cart
إذن خاص لإستخدام عربة الغولف
in the PGA tournaments.
في بطولات الرابطة.
They said, "No.
لقد قالوا، " لا.
Now that would give you an unfair advantage."
لأن ذلك سيعطيك ميزة غير عادلة."
He sued,
رفع دعوى قضائية،
and his case went all the way
وقد أستمرت قضيته
to the Supreme Court, believe it or not,
حتى وصلت للمحكمة العليا، صدقوا أو لا تصدقوا،
the case over the golf cart,
قضية حول عربة الغولف.
because the law says
لأن القانون يقول
that the disabled
بأن المعاق
must be accommodated,
ينبغي أن يتم إستيعابه،
provided the accommodation does not
مع العلم بأن تقديم الإحتياجات لا
change the essential nature
يغيّر من الطبيعة الأساسية
of the activity.
للنشاط.
He says, "I'm a great golfer.
وهو يقول، " أنا لاعب غولف عظيم.
I want to compete.
أرغب بالمنافسة.
But I need a golf cart
لكني بحاجة لعربة غولف
to get from one hole to the next."
لتنقلني من حفرة إلى الأخرى."
Suppose you were
لنفرض أنكم كنتم
on the Supreme Court.
في المحكمة العليا.
Suppose you were deciding
لنفترض أنكم تقررون
the justice of this case.
العدالة في هذه القضية.
How many here would say
كم منكم سيقول
that Casey Martin does have a right to use a golf cart?
بأن كاسي مارتن لديه الحق في إستخدام عربة الغولف؟
And how many say, no, he doesn't?
وكم منكم سيقول، ليس لديه الحق؟
All right, let's take a poll, show of hands.
حسناً، لنجري تصويتاً، أرفعوا ايديكم.
How many would rule in favor of Casey Martin?
كم منكم سيصوتوا لصالح كيسي مارتن؟
And how many would not? How many would say he doesn't?
وكم منكم لا؟ كم منكم سيقولوا ليس لديه الحق؟
All right, we have a good division of opinion here.
حسناً، لدينا إنقسام جيد في الآراء هنا.
Someone who would not
شخص ما لن يؤمّن
grant Casey Martin the right to a golf cart,
لكيسي مارتن حق عربة الغولف،
what would be your reason?
ماذا سيكون سبب رفضك؟
Raise your hand, and we'll try to get you a microphone.
أرفعوا أيديكم، وسنحاول إيصال المايكروفون.
What would be your reason?
ماذا سيكون السبب؟
(Audience: It'd be an unfair advantage.)
(أحد الحضور: إنها ميزة غير عادلة.)
MS: It would be an unfair advantage
مايكل: ستكون ميزة غير عادلة
if he gets to ride in a golf cart.
إذا كان سيركب عربة الغولف.
All right, those of you,
حسناً، أؤلئك منكم،
I imagine most of you who would not give him the golf cart
أتخيل أن معظمكم لن يؤمنوا له عربة الغولف
worry about an unfair advantage.
يقلقون حول الميزة غير العادلة.
What about those of you who say
ماذا عن أؤلئك منكم الذين يقولون
he should be given a golf cart?
ينبغي توفير عربة الغولف له؟
How would you answer the objection?
ماذا سيكون جوابكم على الإعتراض؟
Yes, all right.
نعم، حسناً.
Audience: The cart's not part of the game.
أحد الحضور: العربة ليست جزءاً من اللعبة.
MS: What's your name? (Audience: Charlie.)
مايكل: ما أسمك؟ (أحد الحضور: تشارلي.)
MS: Charlie says --
مايكل: يقول تشارلي--
We'll get Charlie a microphone in case someone wants to reply.
سنحضر لتشارلي مايكروفون في حالة شخص ما يريد الرد.
Tell us, Charlie,
أخبرنا، تشارلي،
why would you say he should be able to use a golf cart?
لماذا ستقول أنه يجب أن يحصل على عربة غولف؟
Charlie: The cart's not part of the game.
تشارلي: العربة ليست جزءاً من اللعبة.
MS: But what about walking from hole to hole?
مايكل: لكن ماذا عن السير من حفرة لحفرة؟
Charlie: It doesn't matter; it's not part of the game.
تشارلي: لا يهم، إنها ليست جزءاً من اللعبة.
MS: Walking the course is not part of the game of golf?
مايكل: السير في الملعب ليست جزءاً من لعبة الغولف؟
Charlie: Not in my book, it isn't.
تشارلي: ليست في كتابي، أليس كذلك.
MS: All right. Stay there, Charlie.
مايكل: حسناً. أبقى هناك، تشارلي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Who has an answer for Charlie?
من لديه رد لتشارلي؟
All right, who has an answer for Charlie?
حسناً، من لديه رد لتشارلي؟
What would you say?
ماذا ستقولين؟
Audience: The endurance element is a very important part of the game,
الحضور: عنصر التحمل هو جزء هام جدا من اللعبة ،
walking all those holes.
السير في كل الحفر.
MS: Walking all those holes?
مايكل: السير في كل تلك الحفر؟
That's part of the game of golf? (Audience: Absolutely.)
ذلك جزء من لعبة الغولف؟ (الحضور: بالطبع.)
MS: What's your name? (Audience: Warren.)
مايكل: ما أسمك؟ (الحضور: وارن.)
MS: Warren.
مايكل: وارن.
Charlie, what do you say to Warren?
تشارلي، ماذا ستقول لوارن؟
Charley: I'll stick to my original thesis.
تشارلي: سأتمسك برسالتي الأصلية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
MS: Warren, are you a golfer?
مايكل: وارن، هل أنت لاعب غولف؟
Warren: I am not a golfer.
وارن: أنا ليس لاعب غولف.
Charley: And I am. (MS: Okay.)
تشارلي: وأنا لاعبة غولف. (مايكل: حسناً.)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You know,
أتعلمون،
it's interesting.
هذا مثير.
In the case, in the lower court,
في القضية، في المحكمة الإبتدائية،
they brought in golfing greats
لقد جلبوا عظماء لعبة الغولف
to testify on this very issue.
للإدلاء بشهادتهم في هذه القضية.
Is walking the course essential to the game?
هل المشي في الملعب أساسي في اللعبة؟
And they brought in Jack Nicklaus and Arnold Palmer.
وقد جاءوا ب "جاك نيكلاوس" و"أرلوند بالمر".
And what do you suppose they all said?
ما الذي يفترض أنهم قالوا؟
Yes. They agreed with Warren.
نعم. لقد أتفقوا مع وارن.
They said, yes, walking the course
لقد قالوا نعم، المشي في الملعب
is strenuous physical exercise.
هو ممارسة الرياضة البدنية الشاقة.
The fatigue factor is an important part of golf.
عنصر التعب هو جزء مهم من لعبة الغولف.
And so it would change
ولذا ستغير
the fundamental nature of the game
الطبيعة الأساسية للعبة
to give him the golf cart.
لنعطيه عربة غولف.
Now, notice,
الآن، لاحظوا،
something interesting --
شئ ما مثير --
Well, I should tell you about the Supreme Court first.
حسناً، ينبغي أن أخبركم عن المحكمة العليا في البداية.
The Supreme Court
المحكمة العليا
decided.
قررت.
What do you suppose they said?
ماذا تفترضوا أنهم قالوا؟
They said yes,
لقد قالوا نعم،
that Casey Martin must be provided a golf cart.
أن كايسي مارتن ينبغي أن يُعطى عربة غولف.
Seven to two, they ruled.
لقد حكموا، سبعة إلى أثنين.
What was interesting about their ruling
ما كان مثيراً حول حكمهم
and about the discussion we've just had
وحول النقاش الذي دخلنا فيه
is that the discussion about
كان النقاش حول
the right, the justice, of the matter
الحقوق، العدالة، في هذه القضية،
depended on
تعتمد على
figuring out what is
التعرف على ما
the essential nature of golf.
هي الطبيعة الأساسية للعبة الغولف.
And the Supreme Court justices
وقضاة المحكمة العليا
wrestled with that question.
تصارعوا مع ذلك السؤال.
And Justice Stevens, writing for the majority,
والقاضي إستيفنس، يكتب للأغلبية،
said he had read all about the history of golf,
قال أنه قرأ عن تاريخ الغولف،
and the essential point of the game
والفكرة الأساسية للعبة
is to get very small ball from one place
هي أن تحرك الكرة الصغيرة من مكان
into a hole
إلى الحفرة
in as few strokes as possible,
بأقل عدد من الضربات الممكنة،
and that walking was not essential, but incidental.
وأن المشي ليس أساسياً، بل عرضي.
Now, there were two dissenters,
الآن، كان هناك أثنين من المنشقين،
one of whom was Justice Scalia.
أحدهم كان القاضي سكاليا.
He wouldn't have granted the cart,
لم يكن ليؤمّن العربة،
and he had a very interesting dissent.
وكان لديه إعتراض مثير للإهتمام.
It's interesting because
إنه مثير لأنه
he rejected the Aristotelian premise
رفض فرضية أرسطو
underlying the majority's opinion.
التي تكمن خلف رأي الأغلبية.
He said it's not possible
لقد قال إنه ليس من الممكن
to determine the essential nature
تحديد الطبيعة الأساسية
of a game like golf.
للعبة مثل الغولف.
Here's how he put it.
هكذا قام بوضعها.
"To say that something is essential
" لنقول أن شئ ما أساسي
is ordinarily to say that it is necessary
هو من العادي أن تقول أنه من الضروري
to the achievement of a certain object.
لتحقيق هدف محدد.
But since it is the very nature of a game
لكن لأن خواص طبيعة اللعبة
to have no object except amusement,
أن لا تحصل على شئ باستثناء التسلية،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
that is, what distinguishes games
ذلك هو، ما يميز الألعاب
from productive activity,
من النشاط الإنتاجي،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
it is quite impossible to say
من الممكن جداً القول
that any of a game's arbitrary rules
أن أي من قواعد اللعبة التعسفية
is essential."
هي أساسية."
So there you have Justice Scalia
إذاً هناك القاضي سكاليا
taking on the Aristotelian premise
يأخذ فرضية أرسطو
of the majority's opinion.
على رأي الأغلبية.
Justice Scalia's opinion
رأي القاضي سكاليا
is questionable
محل شكوك
for two reasons.
لسببين.
First, no real sports fan would talk that way.
أولاً، لا يوجد مشجع رياضة حقيقي يتحدث بتلك الطريقة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If we had thought that the rules
إذا أعتقدنا أن قوانين
of the sports we care about
الألعاب التي نهتم بها
are merely arbitrary,
هي فقط تعسفية،
rather than designed to call forth
بدلاً عن مصممة لتدعو
the virtues and the excellences
الفضائل والميزات
that we think are worthy of admiring,
التي نعتقد أنها تستحق التقدير،
we wouldn't care about the outcome of the game.
فلن نهتم بنتيجة اللعبة.
It's also objectionable
إنه كذلك مرفوض
on a second ground.
على جانب آخر.
On the face of it,
على وجه ذلك،
it seemed to be -- this debate about the golf cart --
إنها تبدو مثل -- هذا الجدل حول عربة الغولف--
an argument about fairness,
حجة حول العدل،
what's an unfair advantage.
ما هي الميزة غير العادلة.
But if fairness were the only thing at stake,
لكن إذا كان العدل هو الشئ الوحيد على المحك،
there would have been an easy and obvious solution.
لكان هناك حل واضح وساهل.
What would it be? (Audience: Let everyone use the cart.)
ماذا سيكون؟ (الحضور: لندع الجميع يستخدم العربة.)
Let everyone ride in a golf cart
لنترك الجميع يركبوا عربة الغولف
if they want to.
إذا أرادوا ذلك.
Then the fairness objection goes away.
عندئذ إعتراض العدل يستبعد تماماً.
But letting everyone ride in a cart
لكن السماح للجميع بركوب عربة
would have been, I suspect,
سيكون، على ما أظن،
more anathema
أكثر لعنة
to the golfing greats
لعظماء الرياضة
and to the PGA,
ولرابطة محترفي الغولف،
even than making an exception for Casey Martin.
أكثر حتى من إستثناء كايسي مارتن.
Why?
لماذا؟
Because what was at stake
لأن ما كان على المحك
in the dispute over the golf cart
في النزاع حول عربة الغولف
was not only the essential nature of golf,
لم يكن فقط الطبيعة الاساسية للغولف،
but, relatedly, the question:
بل، متعلق بالسؤال،
What abilities
ما هي القدرات
are worthy
التي تستحق
of honor and recognition
التقدير والتكريم
as athletic talents?
كرياضي موهوب؟
Let me put the point
دعوني أوضح الفكرة
as delicately as possible:
بدقة أكثر قدر الإمكان:
Golfers are a little sensitive
لاعبو الغولف حساسين قليلاً
about the athletic status of their game.
تجاه الوضع الرياضي للعبتهم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
After all, there's no running or jumping,
بعد كل شئ، ليس هناك جري أو وثب،
and the ball stands still.
والكرة تظل كما هي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So if golfing is the kind of game
إذاً لو كانت لعبة الغولف نوع من الألعاب
that can be played while riding around in a golf cart,
التي يمكن لعبها أثناء الركوب في عربة الغولف،
it would be hard to confer
فسيكون من الصعب الإضفاء
on the golfing greats
على عظماء لعبة الغولف
the status that we confer,
الوضع الذي نضفيه عليهم،
the honor and recognition
التقدير والتكريم
that goes to truly great athletes.
الذي يذهب لعظماء الرياضة الحقيقيون.
That illustrates
ذلك يوضح أنه
that with golf,
مع الغولف،
as with flutes,
كما مع المزامير،
it's hard to decide the question
من الصعب أن تبت في مسألة
of what justice requires,
ما تتطلبه العدالة،
without grappling with the question,
بدون أن تتصارع مع السؤال
"What is the essential nature
" ما هي الطبيعة الأساسية
of the activity in question,
للنشاط مثار الحديث،
and what qualities,
وما هي المقدرات،
what excellences
والصفات
connected with that activity,
المرتبطة بذلك النشاط،
are worthy of honor and recognition?"
وتستحق التكريم والتقدير؟"
Let's take a final example
لنأخذ مثالاً أخيراً
that's prominent in contemporary political debate:
وهو بارز في الجدل السياسي المعاصر:
same-sex marriage.
زواج نفس الجنس.
There are those who favor state recognition
هناك الكثيرون الذين يدعمون إعتراف الدولة
only of traditional marriage
بالزواج التقليدي فقط
between one man and one woman,
بين رجل واحد وإمرأة واحدة،
and there are those who favor state recognition
وهناك أؤلئك الذين يدعمون إعتراف الدولة
of same-sex marriage.
للزواج من نفس الجنس.
How many here
كم منكم هنا
favor the first policy:
يدعمون السياسة الأولى،
the state should recognize traditional marriage only?
الدولة يجب أن تعترف بالزواج التقليدي فقط؟
And how many favor the second, same-sex marriage?
وكم منكم يدعمون، الزواج من نفس الجنس؟
Now, put it this way:
الآن، ضعها بتلك الطريقة،
What ways of thinking
ما هي طرق التفكير
about justice and morality
حول العدالة والأخلاق
underlie the arguments we have
التي تكمن خلف الحجج التي لدينا
over marriage?
حول الزواج؟
The opponents of same-sex marriage say
يقول معارضو الزواج من نفس الجنس
that the purpose of marriage,
أن الهدف من الزواج،
fundamentally, is procreation,
في الأساس، هو الإنجاب،
and that's what's worthy of honoring
وذلك ما يستحق التكريم
and recognizing and encouraging.
والتقدير والتشجيع.
And the defenders of same-sex marriage say no,
والمدافعون عن الزواج لنفس الجنس يقولون لا،
procreation is not the only purpose of marriage;
الإنجاب ليس الهدف الوحيد من الزواج.
what about a lifelong, mutual, loving commitment?
ماذا عن رباط الحب المتبادل والإستمرار مدى الحياة؟
That's really what marriage is about.
ذلك حقاً الهدف من الزواج.
So with flutes, with golf carts,
إذاً مع المزامير، مع عربات الغولف،
and even with a fiercely contested question
وحتى مع مسألة حامية الوطيس
like same-sex marriage,
مثل زواج المثليين،
Aristotle has a point.
لدى أرسطو فكرة.
Very hard to argue about justice
من الصعب جداً النقاش حول العدالة
without first arguing
بدون النقاش أولاً
about the purpose of social institutions
عن الهدف من المؤسسات الإجتماعية
and about what qualities are worthy
وحول الصفات التي تستحق
of honor and recognition.
التكريم والتقدير.
So let's step back from these cases
ولنرجع مرة أخرى من تلك القضايا
and see how they shed light
ونرى كيف أنها سلطت الضوء
on the way we might improve, elevate,
على الطرق التي ربما نحسن بها وترفع،
the terms of political discourse
أساليب الخطاب السياسي
in the United States,
في الولايات المتحدة،
and for that matter, around the world.
ولتلك المسألة، حول العالم.
There is a tendency to think
هناك ميل للإعتقاد
that if we engage too directly
بأننا إذا أدخلنا مباشرة
with moral questions in politics,
الأسئلة الأخلاقية في السياسة،
that's a recipe for disagreement,
فأن ذلك وصفة للخلاف،
and for that matter, a recipe for
ولتلك المسألة، الوصفة ل
intolerance and coercion.
لعدم التسامح والإكراه.
So better to shy away from,
إذاً فمن الأفضل أن نخجل من،
to ignore,
ونتجاهل،
the moral and the religious convictions
الأخلاق والمعتقدات الدينية
that people bring to civic life.
التي يجلبها الناس إلى الحياة المدنية.
It seems to me that our discussion
يبدو لي أن نقاشنا
reflects the opposite,
يعكس عكس ذلك،
that a better way
بأن الطريق الأفضل
to mutual respect
للإحترام المتبادل
is to engage directly
هو الدخول مباشرة
with the moral convictions
مع القناعات الأخلاقية
citizens bring to public life,
التي يجلبها المواطنون إلى الحياة العامة،
rather than to require
بدلاً عن أن نطلب
that people leave their deepest moral convictions
أن يترك الناس قناعاتهم الأخلاقية العميقة
outside politics
خارج السياسة
before they enter.
قبل أن يدخلوا.
That, it seems to me, is a way
ذلك، كما يبدو لي، هو الطريق
to begin to restore
لنبدأ باستعادة
the art of democratic argument.
فن المناظرة الديموقراطية.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
Thanks. Thank you.
شكراً. شكراً لكم.
Chris.
كريس.
Thanks, Chris.
شكراً، كريس.
Chris Anderson: From flutes to golf courses
كريس أندرسون: من المزامير إلى ملاعب الغولف
to same-sex marriage --
لزواج نفس الجنس.
that was a genius link.
كان ذلك ربط عبقري.
Now look, you're a pioneer of open education.
الآن أنظر، أنت رائد في مجال التعليم المفتوح.
Your lecture series was one of the first to do it big.
سلسلة محاضراتك كانت أحد الكبيرة لتفعلها.
What's your vision for the next phase of this?
ما هي رؤيتك للمرحلة القادمة لهذا؟
MS: Well, I think that it is possible.
مايكل: حسناً، أعتقد أن ذلك ممكناً.
In the classroom, we have arguments
في قاعة الدرس، لدينا حجج
on some of the most fiercely held
حول بعض القناعات الأخلاقية
moral convictions that students have
الأشد شراسة التي لدى الطلاب
about big public questions.
حول أسئلة كبيرة عامة.
And I think we can do that in public life more generally.
وأعتقد أننا يمكن أن نفعل ذلك في الحياة العامة بأكثر عمومية.
And so my real dream would be
لذا فحلمي الحقيقي سيكون
to take the public television series
أن نأخذ سلسلة تلفزيونية عامة
that we've created of the course --
التي سجلناها للدرس --
it's available now, online,
إنها متاحة الآن، على الإنترنت،
free for everyone anywhere in the world --
مجاناً للجميع في كل أنحاء العالم --
and to see whether we can partner with institutions,
ونرى سواء يمكن أن نتشارك مع مؤسسات،
at universities in China, in India,
في جامعات في الصين، في الهند،
in Africa, around the world,
في أفريقيا، حول العالم،
to try to promote
لنحاول الترويج
civic education
للتعليم المدني
and also a richer kind
وكذلك نوع أكثر ثراءاً
of democratic debate.
من المناظرة الديموقراطية.
CA: So you picture, at some point,
كريس: إذاً فأنت تتصور، في نقطة ما،
live, in real time,
مباشرة، على الهواء،
you could have this kind of conversation, inviting questions,
يمكنك عقد مثل هذا النوع من النقاش، تستدعي الأسئلة،
but with people from China and India joining in?
مع ناس من الصين والهند يشاركون فيه؟
MS: Right. We did a little bit of it here
مايكل: صحيح. نحن فعل القليل منه هنا
with 1,500 people in Long Beach,
مع 1500 شخص في لونغ بيتش،(مؤتمر تيد)
and we do it in a classroom at Harvard
ونفعله في قاعات المحاضرات في جامعة هارفارد
with about 1,000 students.
مع حوالي 1000 طالب.
Wouldn't it be interesting
ألن يكون مثيراً
to take this way
لنأخذ هذه الطريقة
of thinking and arguing,
للتفكير والتحاجج،
engaging seriously with big moral questions,
المشاركة بكل جدية مع الأسئلة الأخلاقية الكبيرة،
exploring cultural differences
نستكشف الفوارق الثقافية
and connect through a live video hookup,
ونربطها عبر لقطات فيديو مباشرة،
students in Beijing and Mumbai
طلاب في بكين ومومباي
and in Cambridge, Massachusetts
وكمبيردج ،ماساشوستس
and create a global classroom.
ونصنع قاعة محاضرات كونية.
That's what I would love to do.
ذلك ما أحب أن أفعله.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
CA: So, I would imagine
كريس: إذاً، سأتخيل
that there are a lot of people who would love to join you in that endeavor.
هناك الكثير من الناس الذين يحبون الإنضمام لذلك المسعى.
Michael Sandel. Thank you so much. (MS: Thanks so much.)
مايكل ساندل. شكراً جزيلاً لك. (مايكل ساندل: شكراً جزيلاً لك.)